Finding Aid for Joseph L. Sax Papers, 1943-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Joseph L. Sax papers 1943-2013
Sax, Joseph L.
85292 Aa 2
Joseph L. Sax was a Professor of law at the University of Michigan from 1966-1989. Collection includes material relating to the passage of the Michigan Environmental Protection Act of 1970, materials from his career as a legal consultant on environmental issues, course syllabi, lectures, research materials, and manuscripts of published materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
34 linear feet
607 MB online
The collection (Donor No. 6514 ) came to the library in multiple accessions between 1980 and 2014.
The collection is open to research.
"I don't care how good an attorney you are or how many degrees you have if you can't write those standards then don't pass the buck and vote on something that's emotionally acceptable and politically expedient in an election year because this is what the people want and they've been sold on this sue your neighbor bill.
(Comment by Senator in June, 1970 Senate debate on The Michigan Environmental Protection Act.)
"I plead with you to take this first step for posterity, mankind and our grandchildren -- give them a chance... I challenge you to pass the bill."
(comment by private citizen at May, 1970 hearing on the Michigan Environmental Protection Act.)
Joseph Lawrence Sax was a legal scholar who shaped environmental law in the United States by establishing the doctrine that natural resources are a public trust requiring protection.
Sax was born in Chicago, Illinois on February 3, 1936. He graduated from Harvard University in 1957, and the University of Chicago Law School in 1959. Sax was an attorney in Washington D.C. from 1959-1962. He left private practice to teach law at the University of Colorado (1962-1965), the University of Michigan (1966-1986), and the University of California, Berkeley School of Law (1986-2010). From 1994 to 1996, Sax served as Counselor to the Secretary of the Interior and as Deputy Assistant Secretary for Policy at the Department of the Interior under the Clinton Administration. He wrote extensively about environmental law issues and published five books.
Sax received numerous honors including the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency's Environmental Award, the Audubon Society's Conservationist of the Year Award, and the prestigious international Blue Planet Prize in 2007. Sax was a visiting professor at Stanford University, the University of Utah, and the University of Paris. He served as a consultant or board member of nineteen environmental public service organizations. Sax died of complications from a series of strokes on March 9, 2014.
_________________________
Source: Andrew Cohen, Professor and Environmental Law Pioneer Joseph Sax Dies at 78. University of California, Berkeley Law, http://www.law.berkeley.edu/16842.htm.
Beginnings
The history of the "Thomas J. Anderson, Gordon Rockwell Environmental Protection Act of 1970" (MEPA) documented in these files begins with work of Professor Joseph L. Sax of the University of Michigan Law School on the function of the private citizen in societal efforts to enhance and maintain environmental quality. Professor Sax in the 1960's was exploring means of promoting increased citizen participation and was in the process of authoring a book that summarized his thinking Defending the Environment, at the time he was approached by Mrs. Joan Wolfe of the West Michigan Environmental Action Council.
The Council had decided to use a small gift ($1000.00) for the development of legislation that would "give the citizen much greater rights to a livable environment". The specifics of the Council's plan and its requests were put in a letter to Professor Sax on January 28, 1969.
Mrs. Wolfe wrote:
"...unless you show us our error, these are the protections we request of any 'law for the environment'
- that if it incorporates a committee approach to environmental problems, that committee not be merely advisory, unless further protection is built into the law. (mention was made of the right to sue.)
- that the makeup of any environmental committee overwhelmingly represent the vast scientific-ecological-etc. knowledge.
- that vested interests not be included in such a way that they could interfere with an excellent decision-making process ...
Sax's philosophy and theory of effective action to counter pollution differed in some ways from that of the Council." [1] While their objectives were similar, and while both were seeking ways to counter what they perceived as recent defeats for environmental interests in Michigan, Sax wished to avoid creation of another institution. In fact, the overriding principle in Defending the Environment and in much of Sax's thinking on environmental law and policy at the time was that organization-based responses to environmental challenges were doomed to the same failures that had created a need for legislative reform.
Selecting out those points in Mrs. Wolfe's request that indicated skepticism about advisory boards, Sax replied on February 4, 1969:
"The concerns expressed in your letter -- about creating a merely advisory body or one which might become the captive of certain groups with an interest in exploiting the environment are my concerns too, so we will have no disputes about that."
He continued in a spirit that is somewhat surprising in light of the subsequent political history of the MEPA:
" .... one must be politically realistic and not expect too much. Any reform bill will be subject to criticism and efforts at restriction by vested interest groups, both private and public...."
The Council had requested that Sax work on the project as a faculty member of the University of Michigan Law School. Sax responded that he was unable to act either as a representative of the Law School or the University for the Council but that he would be prepared to take on the task in a private capacity. That task -- one that resulted in a law that has been emulated in several states, has generated an immense literature on environmental law and organizational handling of environmental problems, and has been the basis for hundreds of civil suits -was performed in a relatively short time.
Sax drafted the original bill in 3-1/2 work days and sent it to an advisor to the Action Council on February 12, 1969. A return postcard expressed the advisor's pleasure with the draft. The note mentioned, perhaps for the last time by the Council, a "Board of Environmental Review -- for some functions not covered in the bill..."
Mrs. Wolfe added her praises of the draft on March 3, 1969, and the attitude toward litigation of the fledgling Michigan environmental movement moved from acceptance of its necessity as a supplemental activity to enthusiasm:
"It discourages me to think that we can only be protected by having the right to sue - yet I agree that there doesn't seem to be any other way. The fact that we might have that right then becomes terribly exciting and important!"
The original bill
The original bill that Sax wrote contained 7 sections. A summary of the original version is helpful to understanding events in the legislative history of MEPA, The first section stated the name of the Act, "The Natural Resource Conservation and Environmental Protection Act of 1969." Section 2 specified standing under the Statute and the cause of action. Standing was provided for the Attorney General of the State of Michigan, a city, village or town, or any citizen of the State of Michigan. An action for declaratory and equitable relief could be maintained under the new bill by this broad class of plaintiffs, "against any person, including any governmental instrumentality or agency, for the protection of the air, water and other natural resources of the state from pollution, impairment or destruction, or for the protection of the public trust in the natural resources of the state." Section 3 described the burden that the defendant would have once the plaintiff had made a prima facie case: "establishing that there is no feasible and prudent alternative and that the conduct, program or product at issue is consistent with and reasonably required for the promotion of the public health, safety and welfare in light of the state's paramount concern for the protection of its natural resources from pollution, impairment or destruction." Section 4 addressed the appointment of a master or referee and the apportionment of costs for his services.
Section 5 in the original version of the bill was subdivided into 4 subsections. Its preliminary sentence specified the remedies available under the act: temporary and permanent equitable relief or the imposition of conditions. Subsection a addressed remitter, b, the court's power to grant relief when it had remitted an action; c, the retention of jurisdiction upon remitting the action; d, the power of the court to adjudicate the impact when consideration upon remitting had not been adequate. A relatively complicated subsection (section d(ii)) completed §-5:
"Where... judicial review thereof is available, the parties shall be remitted to the processes of such review as augmented by section 6 herein and upon the vesting of jurisdiction in any court of the State of Michigan, the court may thereupon dismiss any action brought hereunder without prejudice to the parties."
Section 6 addressed intervention by the Attorney General of the State of Michigan, a city, village or town, or any citizen of the State of Michigan. Subsection a stated that in the types of procedures addressed in the section, "the agency shall consider the alleged impairment, pollution or destruction of the public trust or air, water or other natural resources. ." Environmentally degrading activity was prohibited under the Act "so long as there is a feasible and prudent alternative consistent with the reasonable requirements of the public health, safety and welfare." Subsection b provided that the court shall grant review of claims that an activity has or is reasonably likely to impair, pollute or destroy the public trust or the air, water or other natural resources of the state. The standards to be followed were those in the Act itself and those authorized by Act No. 197 of the Public Acts of 1952.
Section 7 covered situations arising when a plaintiff or intervenor had not intervened in an applicable non-judicial. proceeding; it indicated circumstances when the court could dismiss the action of the plaintiff or intervenor "with prejudice" for failing "willfully and inexcusably" to so intervene.
From Bill to Law: amendments adopted and proposed
One means of tracing the history of legislation is to compare the original version with the final enrolled bill or statute. While there were changes in the MEPA upon its being passed a year and a half after it was drafted, the basic structure of the bill, despite considerable activity to alter it remained intact.
The changes that did result included the following. The final statute is known as the "Thomas J. Anderson, Gordon Rockwell, Environmental Protection Act of 1970." The Act expands upon the class of possible plaintiffs in the original bill by specifying standing with broad categories, and it [§ 2(2)] describes the function of the court "where there is involved a standard for pollution or for an anti-pollution device or procedure."
The statute addresses venue: an action may be maintained in the Circuit Court having jurisdiction where the alleged violation occurred or is likely to occur. The final version drops the notion of bringing an action "in the name of the State of Michigan" and adds the provision of a surety bond, $500, in situations where "the court has reasonable ground to doubt the solvency of the plaintiff..." MEPA's language regarding the burden of the defendant when a prima facie case has been made differs from that in the original bill adding a sentence regarding "evidence to the contrary" and one specifying some procedural principles to apply to actions under the act. The law seems to separate out the notion of apportionment of costs from the provision of the original bill (section 4) relating to the appointment of a master or referee,
MEPA [§ 4(2)] encompasses a different test for granting temporary relief in remitting an action, and indicates the section of Michigan law that will guide actions once remitted whereas the original bill does not. MEPA makes explicit that the court "may order that additional evidence be taken to the extent necessary to protect the rights recognized in this act." The final version of the bill provides that the court shall maintain jurisdiction where judicial review is available "as to any administrative, licensing or other proceeding."
The intervention provision in the MEPA (§ 5) is weaker than in Sax's original draft (§ 6). The doctrines of collateral estoppel and res judicata are added in the final version to prevent multiplicity of suits. Language relating to the public trust is altered as well. The enacted bill governs "the protection of the air, water and other natural resources and the public trust therein from pollution, impairment or destruction" as opposed to ways, of phrasing in the first form: the "public trust or air, water" and "public trust in the natural resources of the state." The final version eliminates language relating to the supplementary nature of the act and the standards to follow in judicial. review and procedures to apply when a party has failed to intervene. The date upon which the act will become effective, October 1, 1970, is added as is a statement that the act will have "immediate effect," and other minor changes are made.
Much of the controversy surrounding the Act is not reflected by this simple comparison of the bill with the final statute. Proposed amendments and attempts to add language that did not ultimately become part of the statute were numerous. Strong opposition to the concepts codified in MEPA was carried all the way through the legislative process to the Michigan Senate Debate on H.B. 3055 on June 26, 1970. A summary of that debate follows before a look at major events in the legislative history of the Act.
The Senate Debate
... it's like asking a carpenter to take out somebody's appendix... 11
(Comment by Senator in June, 1970 Senate debate on the Michigan Environmental Protection Act.)
A major question in the Senate debate was over the role of the judiciary: whether the powers H.B. 3055 proposed would effect a proper exercise of judicial authority. The first issue relating to this general concern addressed by the Senate was whether courts were technically qualified to make the determinations that the House bill empowered them to make. Senators Bowman (P. 7) [2] and Hubert (p. 35) voiced the opinion that courts lack the basic technical knowledge to rule on the types of issues likely to arise in MEPA actions. Decisions, they felt, would better be made by administrative agencies which they believed possess necessary expertise and experience. The Senate as a whole, however, concurred with the bill's underlying philosophy that the judiciary could competently perform the role required of it under H.B. 3055.
Related to this controversy was one that concerned a specific judicial power, the courts' ability under Sec. 2, subsection (2) (b) (of the statute) to direct the adoption of a standard approved and specified by a court when it found an agency-imposed standard to be deficient. Some Senators asserted that courts were being told to assume a rule-making function. Senator Gray stated that courts should have the right to determine the validity of the rules, but not the right to make the rules (p. 18).
An interpretation of this subsection offered by Senator Brown preceded the defeat of a proposed amendment to delete the subsection. Brown argued that the courts would not promulgate the standards themselves. The courts' function would be to force agencies to adopt standards that would comply with the public interest in a clean environment. Brown argued that the imposition of a court-ordered standard would have created difficulties in respect to the procedure that had to be followed (prior to the adoption of any new standard) under the Administrative Procedures Act of 1969. Brown's long and detailed explanation was highlighted by a convincing conclusion to a hypothetical case involving the Department of Agriculture:
"What it really amounts to is pressure on the agency at that point to bring the standard up to date, and we have no such pressure now... And I think the public, if they establish that doing the action complained about is in violation of the public trust and that the standard itself is invalid and unreasonable, they ought to have a lever to urge the agency, and I think that's about all they could do, urge the agency to come up with a standard. Now I don't know what happens if the agency refuses to act. I suppose the court at some point could hold the director of Agriculture in contempt. I don't think that's likely to happen."
The rights of plaintiffs and defendants under H.B. 3055 were also debated. The Senate addressed res judicata and collateral estoppel. While it was recognized that these two doctrines presumably would have been applied by the courts without explicit language in the bill (Brown, p. 2), the language was added to emphasize the legislature's concern about possible frivolous suits and to indicate to the courts that they should be sensitive to harassment.
The Senate acted to protect industry defendants from "harassment" by another device as well. An amendment was passed requiring a surety bond not to exceed $500.00 if the court had reasonable grounds to doubt a plaintiff's solvency or his ability to pay any judgment that might be rendered against him, The surety bond, as opposed to a personal bond, it was pointed out in the debate (pp. 21-22), requires that someone or some organization actually has the financial ability to back up the bond.
Senator Brown in the debate also delineated the difference between suits brought under H.B. 3055 and nuisance actions (p. 3): in common law nuisance actions, plaintiffs have standing only if they can show injury to themselves or their property. Under H.B. 3055, no such requirement is imposed.
Venue was discussed. Senator Mack (p. 3) feared that actions could be brought by plaintiffs anywhere in the state. Senator Brown replied that ordinary rules of venue would apply, that suits would have to be brought in the county where the alleged pollution or threatened pollution existed. The Senate then amended the act to make this clear.
Considerable discussion focused on the language of sec. 3 subsection (1) (final version) which reads in part that after, the plaintiff has made a prima facie showing that the defendant has, or is likely to, pollute, impair, or destroy the air, water, or other natural resource or the public trust therein, the defendant "may also show, by way of an affirmative defense, that there is no feasible and prudent alternative to defendant's conduct and that such conduct is consistent with the promotion of the public health, safety, and welfare." (emphasis added). The key word in the above phrase is the underlined "and".) Opponents of this language proposed that "or" be inserted in place of "and". This was intended to create alternative affirmative defenses rather than dual requirements for a single affirmative defense.
The change was proposed because of a fear that situations would arise in which an industry or a public service organization (such as a hospital or a power company) utilizing the best available technology, thereby satisfying the first requirement, would yet run afoul of the second requirement. It was hypothesized that the dual requirement would force a shutdown of the service or industry in these situations
Senator Brown asserted again that the courts would not be so rigid in their interpretation of this provision. He argued that the dual requirement would give courts flexibility in molding solutions to problems because they were allowed to look at whether
an activity was in the interest of public health, welfare, and safety as well as whether the best available technology was being employed. The "and" language was retained by the Senate, ending one of the longest and most forcefully contested disagreements in consideration of the "Sax bill."
Other Proposed Amendments
In addition to those debated by the full Senate, several. other weakening amendments were considered in the 15 months from the time that the bill was originally introduced by Representative Thomas Anderson until its passage. At one point in the process Representative Rohlfs moved to amend the bill: "section 2A. if the court has reasonable ground to doubt the solvency of the plaintiff or the plaintiff's ability to pay any cost or judgment which might be rendered against him in an action brought under this act the court may order the plaintiff to post bond to cover such cost or judgment". This amendment was defeated (roll call no. 332) by a vote of 28 to 57 in the House. Because of its open-ended form, it might have been a major inhibiting factor in bringing litigation -- especially for those plaintiffs whose resources were relatively limited.
Always controversial about the bill was the relationship of the remedies that the court could impose to existing standards, such as those that had been created by an administrative agency. An amendment by Representative Geerlings would have changed the bill as follows:
"Section 7. Where standards of pollution are provided by law, they shall form the basis for determining pollution under this _Act".
While on its face this amendment would not seem to greatly limit judicial power, the change was considered highly unfavorable by proponents of the legislation. It was precisely because of the inadequacy of existing standards that the coalition for the passage of the citizen environmental law suit had evolved. The amendment was defeated in the House by a vote of 38 to 62. (Roll Call no. 334).
The attempt to limit the bill's effectiveness to apply only to situations where pollution was considered "unreasonable" was made again and again. In fact, early on, "unreasonable" was added as a descriptor in every section of the bill preceding "pollution". It took an amendment to delete this word from the final version of the bill.
As the bill made its way through the Michigan Legislature, language limiting its effect came and went. One version, a substitute for the original house bill, would have added the phrase "considering all relevant surrounding circumstances and factors" following "feasible and prudent alternative," and in other sections of the bill. This language was not eliminated until the Second Substitute for H.B. 3055. [3]
From Bill to Law: major events in the legislative process
Another means of chronicling the legislative history of the Act is to describe the political events in its passage. A brief summary follows.
In Fall and Winter, 1969, with the Sax draft in hand, the Action Council began work on a strategy for introducing the bill into the Michigan legislature and for passage in substantially its original form. At first a Republican member of the House was approached to guide the bill. Because of the minority status of his party in the legislature he suggested an alternative sponsor. His advice and the advice of a Department of Natural Resources (DNR) commissioner whom the Action Council had contacted led to the selection of Democrat Thomas Anderson to steer MEPA through the Michigan House.